<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
  which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. --><!ENTITY DATAREQ SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel.xml">
<!ENTITY DATAPROTO SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-protocol.xml">
<!ENTITY DCSDPNEG SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg.xml">
<!ENTITY SDPSCTP SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mmusic-sctp-sdp.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4566 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4566.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4975 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4975.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5547 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5547.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6135 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6135.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6714 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6714.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7977 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7977.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
  please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
  (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-17" ipr="trust200902" updates="RFC4975">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
  ipr values: trust200902, noModificationTrust200902, noDerivativesTrust200902,
  or pre5378Trust200902
  you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
  they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

 <front>
  <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the
       full title is longer than 39 characters -->

  <title abbrev="MSRP over Data Channels">
                 MSRP over Data Channels
  </title>

  <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

  <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

  <author initials="J. M." surname="Recio" fullname="Jose M. Recio" role="editor">
   <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>
   <address>
    <email>jose@ch3m4.com
    </email>
   </address>
  </author>

  <author initials="C." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
   <organization>Ericsson</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
     <city>Jorvas 02420</city>
     <region/>
     <country>Finland</country>
    </postal>
    <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>

  <date year="2020"/>

  <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, 
   xml2rfc will fill
   in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill
   in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is
   necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for 
   the purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient 
   to specify just the year. -->

  <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

  <area>ART</area>

  <workgroup>MMUSIC</workgroup>

  <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
    IETF is fine for individual submissions.
    If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
    which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->


  <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
    files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
    output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
    keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

  <abstract>

   <t>This document specifies how the Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) can be transported as a WebRTC data channel sub-protocol, using the SDP offer/answer generic data channel negotiation framework to establish such a channel. Two network configurations are supported: connecting two MSRP over data channel endpoints; and a gateway configuration, connecting an MSRP over data channel endpoint with an MSRP over TCP or TLS endpoint. This document updates RFC4975</t>

  </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>
  <section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">

   <t>The Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) <xref target="RFC4975"/> is a protocol for transmitting a series of related instant messages in the context of a session. In addition to instant messaging, MSRP can also be used for image sharing or file transfer. MSRP was initially defined in <xref target="RFC4975"/> to work over TCP and TLS connections, and over a WebSocket subprotocol specified by <xref target="RFC7977"/>.</t>

   <t>This document specifies the negotiation and transport of MSRP over a WebRTC data channel <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/>. Negotiation is carried out as specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/> and MSRP is transported as a sub-protocol of a WebRTC data channel, without the TCP and TLS layers.</t>

   <t>Defining MSRP as a data channel sub-protocol has many benefits:
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>provides to applications a proven protocol enabling instant messaging, file transfer, image sharing</t>
     <t>integrates those features with other WebRTC voice, video and data features</t>
     <t>leverages the SDP-based negotiation already defined for MSRP</t>
     <t>allows the interworking with MSRP endpoints running on a TCP or TLS connection</t>
    </list>
   </t>

   <t>Compared to WebSockets, which provide a message passing protocol to applications with no direct access to TCP or TLS sockets, data channels provide a low latency transport, leverage NAT-aware connectivity and security features of WebRTC, and are increasingly available not only in modern browsers but in other applications that use WebRTC for media or other purposes, such as IoT or telemetry in general, non-media data exchange, and so on.</t>

   <t>Considering an MSRP endpoint as an MSRP application that uses a WebRTC data channel, this document describes two configurations where the other endpoint is respectively either another MSRP over data channel endpoint (e.g., a WebRTC application) or an MSRP endpoint using either TCP or TLS transport.</t>

   <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC4975"/> as described in <xref target="updates-to-rfc4975"/>.</t>

  </section>

  <section title="Conventions">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
 </section>

  <section title="WebRTC Data Channel Considerations">

   <section title="MSRP Data Channel" anchor="msrp-data-channel">
    <t>In this document, an MSRP data channel is a data channel for which the instantiated sub-protocol is "MSRP", and where the channel is negotiated using the SDP-based external negotiation method defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>.</t>
    <t>The following WebRTC data channel property values <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/> apply to a MSRP data channel:</t>
    <texttable title="">
      <ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
      <ttcol align="left">Value</ttcol>
      <c>Subprotocol Identifier</c>
      <c>msrp</c>
      <c>Transmission reliability</c>
      <c>reliable</c>
      <c>Transmission order</c>
      <c>in-order</c>
      <c>Label</c>
      <c>See 
        <xref target="use-of-dcmap-attribute"/>
      </c>
    </texttable>
   </section>

  </section>

  <section title="SDP Considerations" anchor="sdp-cons">
     <t>This section describes the SDP considerations which are specific to a MSRP data channel</t>
     <section title="MSRP URI">
      <t>This document extends the MSRP URI syntax <xref target="RFC4975"/> by defining the new transport parameter value "dc":</t>
       <figure align="left" title="">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
  transport  /= "dc"
                ; Add "dc" to existing transports per [RFC4975] ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
      <t>MSRP design provides for new transport bindings, see Section 6 of <xref target="RFC4975"/>, MSRP implementations are expected to allow unrecognized transports for which there is no need to establish a connection to the resource described by the URI, as it's the case of data channels (<xref target="use-of-dcsa-attribute"/>).</t>
     </section>
     <section title="msrp-scheme">
      <t>The msrp-scheme portion of the MSRP-URI that represents an MSRP data channel endpoint (used in the SDP path attribute and in the MSRP message headers) is always "msrps", which indicates that the MSRP data channel is always secured using DTLS as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/>.</t>
     </section>

     <section title="Use of the dcmap Attribute" anchor="use-of-dcmap-attribute">

      <t>An offerer and answerer SHALL, in each offer and answer, include a dcmap attribute line (<xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>) within the media description of the SCTP association for each MSRP data channel session to be negotiated.</t>

      <t>The attribute includes the following data channel parameters:
       <list style="symbols">
        <t>"label=" labelstring</t>
        <t>"subprotocol=" "msrp"</t>
       </list>
      </t>

      <t>The labelstring is set by the MSRP application according to <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>.</t>

      <t>The offerer and answerer SHALL NOT include the max-retr and the max-time attribute parameters in the dcmap attribute.</t>
      
      <t>The offerer and answerer MAY include the ordered attribute parameter in the dcmap attribute. If included, the attribute parameter value SHALL be set to "true".</t>

      <t>Below is an example of the dcmap attribute for an MSRP session to be negotiated with stream-id=2 and label="chat":</t>

      <figure align="left" title="">
       <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
a=dcmap:2 label="chat";subprotocol="msrp"
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

     </section>

     <section title="Use of the dcsa Attribute" anchor="use-of-dcsa-attribute">

      <t>
        An offerer and answerer SHALL, in each offer and answer, include a dcsa attribute line (<xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>) 
        within the media description for the SCTP association for each MSRP-specific SDP attribute to be negotiated for each MSRP data channel being negotiated.
      </t>

      <t>
        An offerer and answerer SHALL include a dcsa attribute for each of the following MSRP-specific SDP attributes:
       <list style="symbols">
        <t>defined in <xref target="RFC4975"/>: "path".</t>
        <t>defined in <xref target="RFC6714"/>: "msrp-cema".</t>
        <t>defined in <xref target="RFC6135"/>: "setup". See <xref target="use-of-setup-attribute"/></t>
       </list>
      </t>
      <t>
        It is considered a protocol error if one or more of the dcsa embedded attributes listed above are not included in an offer or answer.
      </t>

      <t>An offerer and answerer MAY include a dcsa attribute for any of the following MSRP-specific SDP attributes, following the procedures defined for each attributes:
       <list style="symbols">
        <t>defined in <xref target="RFC4975"/>: "accept-types", "accept-wrapped-types" and "max-size"</t>
        <t>defined in <xref target="RFC4566"/>: "sendonly", "recvonly", "inactive" and "sendrecv"</t>
        <t>defined in <xref target="RFC5547"/>: all the parameters related to MSRP file transfer. See <xref target="file_transfer_sdp"/>.</t>
       </list>
      </t>

      <t>A subsequent offer or answer MAY update the previously negotiated MSRP subprotocol attributes while keeping the same subprotocol a=dcmap description. The semantics for newly negotiated MSRP subprotocol attributes are per <xref target="RFC4975"/>.</t>

      <t>When MSRP messages are transported on a data channel, the "path" attribute is not used for routing of the messages. The MSRP data channel is established using the SDP offer/answer procedures defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>, and the MSRP messages are then transported on that data channel. This is different from legacy MSRP <xref target="RFC4975"/> but similar to MSRP CEMA <xref target="RFC6714"/>. However, when an endpoint receives an MSRP message over a data channel, it MUST still perform the MSRP-URI comparison procedures defined in <xref target="RFC4975"/>.</t>
     
     </section>


     <section title="Use of the dcsa embedded setup Attribute" anchor="use-of-setup-attribute">

      <t>
        As described in <xref target="use-of-dcsa-attribute"/>, the usage of a dsca embedded setup attribute is mandated for MSRP sessions over data channels. 
        It is used to negotiate which MSRP session endpoint assumes the active role as per Section 4.2.2 of <xref target="RFC6135"/> and
        Section 5.4 of <xref target="RFC4975"/>. It has no relationship with the DTLS connection establishment roles <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-sctp-sdp"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
        The dcsa embedded setup attribute is of the form "a=dcsa:x setup:&lt;role&gt;", with x being the data channel's SCTP stream identifier, so that
        such attribute is explicitly associated with an MSRP session over a specific data channel.
      </t>

     </section>

    <section title="Session Closing" anchor="session-closing-sdp">
     <t>An MSRP session is closed by closing the associated data channel, following the procedures in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>.</t>
     <t>The port value for the "m=" line SHOULD NOT be changed (e.g. to zero) when closing an MSRP session (unless all data channels are being closed and the SCTP association is no longer needed), since this would close the SCTP association and impact all of the data channels. In all cases in <xref target="RFC4975"/> where the procedure calls for setting the port to zero for the MSRP "m=" line in an SDP offer for TCP transport, the SDP offerer of an MSRP session with data channel transport SHALL remove the corresponding dcmap and dcsa attributes.</t>
     <t>The SDP answerer must ensure that no dcmap or dcsa attributes are present in the SDP answer if no corresponding attributes are present in the received SDP offer.</t>
    </section>

     <section title="Support for MSRP File Transfer Function" anchor="file_transfer_sdp">
       <t>SDP attributes specified in <xref target="RFC5547"/> for a file transfer "m=" line are embedded as subprotocol-specific attributes using the syntax defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>.</t>
     </section>

     <section title="Example SDP Negotiation" anchor="example-sdp-negotiation">

      <t>The following is an example of an "m=" line for data channels in an SDP offer that includes the attributes needed to establish two MSRP sessions: one for chat and one for file transfer. The example is derived from a combination of examples in <xref target="RFC4975"/> and <xref target="RFC5547"/>.</t>

      <figure align="left" title="">
       <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
   m=application 54111 UDP/DTLS/SCTP webrtc-datachannel
   c=IN IP4 198.51.100.79
   a=max-message-size:100000
   a=sctp-port:5000
   a=setup:actpass
   a=fingerprint:SHA-1 \
       4A:AD:B9:B1:3F:82:18:3B:54:02:12:DF:3E:5D:49:6B:19:E5:7C:AB
   a=tls-id:4a756565cddef001be82
   a=dcmap:0 label="chat";subprotocol="msrp"
   a=dcsa:0 msrp-cema
   a=dcsa:0 setup:active
   a=dcsa:0 accept-types:message/cpim text/plain
   a=dcsa:0 path:msrps://198.51.100.79:54111/si438dsaodes;dc
   a=dcmap:2 label="file transfer";subprotocol="msrp"
   a=dcsa:2 sendonly
   a=dcsa:2 msrp-cema
   a=dcsa:2 setup:active
   a=dcsa:2 accept-types:message/cpim
   a=dcsa:2 accept-wrapped-types:*
   a=dcsa:2 path:msrps://198.51.100.79:54111/jshA7we;dc
   a=dcsa:2 file-selector:name:"picture1.jpg" \
        type:image/jpeg size:1463440 hash:sha-1:\
        FF:27:0D:81:14:F1:8A:C3:35:3B:36:64:2A:62:C9:3E:D3:6B:51:B4
   a=dcsa:2 file-transfer-id:rjEtHAcYVZ7xKwGYpGGwyn5gqsSaU7Ep
   a=dcsa:2 file-disposition:attachment
   a=dcsa:2 file-date:creation:"Mon, 12 Jan 2018 15:01:31 +0800"
   a=dcsa:2 file-icon:cid:id2@bob.example.com
   a=dcsa:2 file-range:1-1463440
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

     </section>
  </section>


  <section title="MSRP Considerations" anchor="msrp-cons">

   <t>The procedures specified in <xref target="RFC4975"/> apply except when this document specifies otherwise. This section describes the MSRP considerations specific to a MSRP data channel.</t>
    <section title="Session Mapping">
      <t>In this document, each MSRP session maps to one data channel exactly.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Session Opening" anchor="session-opening-msrp">
     <t><xref target="use-of-setup-attribute"/> describes how the active MSRP session endpoint role is negotiated. The active MSRP session endpoint uses the data channel established for this MSRP session by the generic data channel opening procedure defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>.</t>
     <t>As soon as the WebRTC data channel is opened, the MSRP session is actually opened by the active MSRP session endpoint. In order to do this the active MSRP endpoint sends an MSRP SEND message (empty or not) to the other MSRP endpoint.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Session Closing" anchor="session-closing">
     <t>The closure of an MSRP session SHALL be signaled via SDP following the requirements in <xref target="session-closing-sdp"/></t>
     <t>If the data channel used to transport the MSRP session fails and gets torn down, the endpoints SHALL consider the MSRP session failed. An MSRP endpoint MAY, based on local policy, try to negotiate a new MSRP data channel.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Data Framing" anchor="data-framing">
     <t>Each text-based MSRP message is sent on the corresponding SCTP stream using standard MSRP framing and chunking procedures, as defined in <xref target="RFC4975"/>, with each MSRP chunk delivered in a single SCTP user message. Therefore all sent MSRP chunks including the MSRP chunk header SHALL have lengths of less than or equal to the value of the peer's "a=max-message-size" attribute, which is associated with the data channel's SCTP association.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Data Sending, Receiving and Reporting">
      <t>Data sending, receiving and reporting procedures SHALL conform to <xref target="RFC4975"/>.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Support for MSRP File Transfer Function" anchor="file_transfer_msrp">
     <t><xref target="RFC5547"/> defines an end-to-end file transfer method based on MSRP and the SDP offer/answer mechanism. This file transfer method is also usable by MSRP endpoints using data channels, with the following considerations:
      <list style="symbols">
       <t>As an MSRP session maps to one data channel, a file transfer session maps also to one data channel.</t>
       <t>SDP attributes are negotiated as specified in <xref target="file_transfer_sdp"/>.</t>
       <t>Once the file transfer is complete, the same data channel MAY be reused for another file transfer.</t>
      </list>
     </t>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Gateway Considerations" anchor="gateway-cons">

   <t>This section describes the network configuration where one MSRP endpoint uses a MSRP data channel as MSRP transport, the other MSRP endpoint uses TLS/TCP connections as MSRP transport, and the two MSRP endpoints interwork via a gateway.</t>

   <t>Specifically, a gateway can be configured to interwork an MSRP session over a data channel with a peer that does not support data channel transport in one of two ways.</t>

   <t>In one model, the gateway performs as a MSRP B2BUA to interwork all the procedures as necessary between the endpoints.  No further specification is needed for this model.</t>

   <t>Alternately, the gateway can provide transport level interworking between MSRP endpoints using different transport protocols. In accordance with <xref target="use-of-dcsa-attribute"/>, path attributes SHALL NOT be used for transport level interworking.</t>

   <t>When the gateway performs transport level interworking between MSRP endpoints, all of the procedures in <xref target="msrp-cons"/> and <xref target="sdp-cons"/> apply to each peer, with the following additions:

    <list style="symbols">
     <t>The gateway SHALL use CEMA towards the non-data channel endpoint.</t>
     <t>If the non-data channel endpoint does not support CEMA, transport level interworking mode is not possible, the gateway needs to act as an MSRP B2BUA.</t>
     <t>The gateway SHALL NOT modify the path attribute received from data channel or from non-data channel endpoints.</t>
     <t>The gateway SHALL NOT modify the setup value received from data channel or from non-data channel endpoints.</t>
     <t>The endpoint establishing an MSRP session using data channel transport SHALL NOT request inclusion of any relays, although it MAY interoperate with a peer that signals the use of relays.</t>
    </list>

   </t>

  </section>

  <section title="Updates to RFC4975" anchor="updates-to-rfc4975">
    <t>This document updates <xref target="RFC4975"/>, by allowing the usage of the "msrps" scheme when the underlying connection is protected with DTLS.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

   <t>MSRP traffic over data channels is secured, including confidentiality, integrity and source authentication, as specified by <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/></t>

   <t>Note that discussion in <xref target="RFC4975"/> on MSRP message attribution to remote identities applies to data channel transport.</t>

  </section>

  <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

   <section title="msrps URI scheme" anchor="IANA-reg-msrps">
     <t>This document modifies the usage of the msrps URI scheme, registered by <xref target="RFC4975"/>, adding DTLS as a protected transport indicated by the URI scheme.
     </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Subprotocol Identifier MSRP" anchor="IANA-reg-MSRP">

    <t>This document adds a reference to the subprotocol identifier "msrp" in the "WebSocket Subprotocol Name Registry"
    </t>

   </section>

   <section title="setup Attribute" anchor="IANA-reg-setup">

       <t>NOTE to RFC Editor: Please replace "XXXX" with the number of this RFC.
     </t>

     <t>This document modifies the usage of the SDP setup attribute, if this attribute is embedded in a dcsa attribute and associated with an MSRP session over a data channel. The modified usage is described in <xref target="use-of-setup-attribute"/>.
     </t>

     <t>Usage level "dcsa(MSRP)" should be added to the IANA registration of the SDP setup attribute as follows:
     </t>

     <texttable title="">
       <ttcol align="left" width="35%"/>
       <ttcol align="left" width="65%"/>

       <c>Contact name:</c>
       <c>IESG</c>

       <c>Contact email:</c>
       <c>iesg@ietf.org</c>

       <c>Attribute name:</c>
       <c>setup</c>

       <!--
       <c>Attribute syntax:</c>
       <c>unchanged</c>
       -->

       <!--
       <c>Attribute semantics:</c>
       <c>unchanged</c>
       -->

       <c>Usage level:</c>
       <c>dcsa(MSRP)</c>

       <!--
       <c>Charset dependent:</c>
       <c>unchanged</c>
       -->

       <c>Purpose:</c>
       <c> Negotiate the active role of an MSRP session over a data channel as per 
       <xref target="use-of-setup-attribute"/>
       </c>

       <!--
       <c>Appropriate values:</c>
       <c>unchanged</c>
       -->

       <!--
       <c>O/A procedures:</c>
       <c>unchanged</c>
       -->

       <!--
       <c>Mux category:</c>
       <c>unchanged</c>
       -->

       <c>Reference:</c>
       <c>RFCXXXX</c>
     </texttable>

   </section>
  </section>

  <section title="Acknowledgments">

   <t>The authors wish to acknowledge the borrowing of ideas from another internet draft by Peter Dunkley and Gavin Llewellyn, and to thank Flemming Andreasen, Christian Groves, Paul Kyzivat, Jonathan Lennox, Uwe Rauschenbach, Albrecht Schwarz, and Keith Drage for their invaluable comments.</t>
   <t>Richard Ejzak, Keith Drage and Juergen Stoetzer-Bradler contributed an earlier version, before the draft was re-adopted.</t>
   <t>Julien Maisonneuve helped with the re-adoption of the draft, and  Maridi R. Makaraju (Raju) contributed valuable comments after the draft was re-adopted.</t>

  </section>

 <section title="CHANGE LOG">

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-16'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>WGLC review: draft updates RFC4975; clarify introduction; rewrite wording on path and transport negotiation; session closing clarifications; references cleanup.</t>
     <t>Editorial: consistent SHALL usage; reorder updates, security and IANA sections for consistency; typos; acknowledgements.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-15'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>More concise and clear introduction and section descriptions.</t>
     <t>Updates on author list, contributions and acknowledgements.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-14'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Reorganization following t140-usage-data-channel structure.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-13'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Clarify gateway procedures in accordance to mandatory use of CEMA.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-12'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Make CEMA mandatory, clarify SDP procedures.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-11'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Additional clarifications on cema and path attribute after mail list feedback.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-10'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Corrections and clarifications on cema and path attributes after mail list feedback.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-09'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Corrected area to ART.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-08'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Updated reference to 4566bis.</t>
     <t>Expanded motivation paragraphs in introduction.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-07'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Move security considerations after IANA considerations, following RFC7322 suggested order.</t>
     <t>Update references to use xml.resource.org citation database.</t>
     <t>Reformat of the section discussing setup parameter</t>
     <t>Align examples with latest <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/> draft.</t>
     <t>Edit section 6 for clarity.</t>
     <t>Security requirements.</t>
     <t>Clarify comment on unrecognized transports and session opening.</t>
     <t>Update year, add editor.</t>

    </list>
   </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-06'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">

     <t>Modification of Keith's address information.
     </t>

    </list>
   </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-05'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">

     <t>Modification of Juergen's address information.
     </t>

    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-04'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">

     <t>Addition of "I-D.ietf-mmusic-rfc4566bis"/>
     to list of normative references.
     </t>

     <t>Addition of <xref target="IANA-reg-setup"/> as per section 8.2.4 
     of "I-D.ietf-mmusic-rfc4566bis"/>.
     </t>

    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-03'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">

     <t>Addition of IANA registration related <xref target="IANA-reg-MSRP"/>.
     </t>

    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-02'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">

     <t>Addition of "a=setup:actpass", "a=connection:new", "a=fingerprint:..." and "a=dcsa:x setup=active" SDP attributes to the SDP example in <xref target="example-sdp-negotiation"/>.
     </t>

     <t>Addition of "RFC4145" and <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-sctp-sdp"/> to list of normative references.
     </t>

     <t>Addition of new <xref target="use-of-setup-attribute"/> describing how the active MSRP session endpoint role is negotiated.
     </t>

     <t>Extension of first paragraph of session-opening with new first sentence "<xref target="use-of-setup-attribute"/> describes how the active MSRP session endpoint role is negotiated.".
     </t>

     <t>First sentence of second paragraph in session-opening was "As soon as this data channel is opened, the MSRP session is actually opened by the active MSRP endpoint which sends an MSRP SEND message (empty or not) to the other MSRP endpoint." Replacement of this sentence with "As soon as this data channel is opened, the MSRP session is actually opened by the active MSRP endpoint. In order to do this the active MSRP endpoint sends an MSRP SEND message (empty or not) to the other MSRP endpoint."
     </t>

     <t>Addition of setup attribute specific behavior descriptions of data channel to TCP or TLS interworking gateways in <xref target="gateway-cons"/>.
     </t>

    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-01'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">

     <t>In the abstract replacement of the first sentence "This document specifies how the Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) can be instantiated as a data channel sub-protocol, using the SDP offer/answer exchange-based external negotiation defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>" with "This document specifies how the Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP) can be instantiated as a data channel sub-protocol, using the SDP offer/answer exchange-based generic data channel negotiation framework" in order to remove the reference from the abstract text.
     </t>

     <t>Addition of following sentence to the second paragraph in <xref target="introduction"/>: "The MSRP protocol negotiation defined in this document is based on the generic SDP offer/answer exchange based data channel negotiation as specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>".
     </t>

     <t>In <xref target="msrp-data-channel"/> replacement of sub-protocol identifier "msrp" with "MSRP" in order to make this consistent with the formal specification in 
<xref target="use-of-dcmap-attribute"/>.
     </t>

     <t>Throughout the text replacement of "shall" with "SHALL" etc where appropriate as per <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
     </t>

     <t>In <xref target="use-of-dcmap-attribute"/> replacement of sentence 'The max-retr, max-time and ordered parameters shall not be used.' with 'Ordered and reliable data channels MUST always be used, such that the "max-retr" and "max-time" parameters SHALL NOT be used. If the "ordered" parameter is used, then its value MUST be equal to "true".'.
     </t>

     <t>In <xref target=" use-of-dcmap-attribute"/> removal of "(on default SCTP port 5000)" from the sentence preceding the example "a=dcmap" attribute line.
     </t>

     <t>In <xref target="use-of-dcsa-attribute"/> first paragraph was "The SDP offer shall also include a dcsa attribute line (defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>) within the media description for the SCTP association for each MSRP-specific SDP attribute to be negotiated for each MSRP data channel being negotiated.". Replacement of this paragraph with "The SDP offer SHALL also include within the media description for the SCTP association a dcsa attribute line (defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>) for each MSRP-specific SDP attribute to be negotiated for each MSRP data channel being negotiated.".
     </t>

     <t>Appended following sentence at the end of the first paragraph of <xref target="data-framing"/>: "Therefore all sent MSRP chunks MUST have lengths of less than or equal to the value of the peer's "a=max-message-size" attribute, which is associated with the data channel's SCTP association.".
     </t>

     <t>Addition of the previously missing colon to the "a=sctp-port" attribute line in <xref target="example-sdp-negotiation"/>.
     </t>

     <t>In <xref target="session-closing"/> replacement of the first paragraph "Closing of an MSRP session is done using the generic data channel closing procedure defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>." with 'The closure of an MSRP session MUST be signaled via an SDP offer/answer exchange which removes the "a=dcmap:" and "a=dcsa:" attribute lines associated with the MSRP session from the associated DTLS/SCTP based media description. This results in the associated data channel being closed as well as per <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>, where the actual data channel closure procedure is typically initiated by the SDP answerer right after having accepted the SDP offer.'.
     </t>

    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ietf-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-00'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">

     <t>Additional reference to <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/> in list of normative references.</t>

     <t>Replacement of previous document title "MSRP over SCTP/DTLS data channels" with "MSRP over Data Channels" in order to align with the terminology used in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg"/>.</t>

     <t>In "terminology", "WebRTC data channel" was defined as "A bidirectional channel consisting of paired SCTP outbound and inbound streams." Replacement of this definition with "Data channel: A WebRTC data channel as specified in <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/>", and consistent usage of either "data channel" or "MSRP data channel" in the remainder of the document."</t>

     <t>In the introduction replacement of references to <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-protocol"/> with a reference to <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-data-channel"/>.</t>

     <t>Consistent usage of '"m=" line' in whole document as per <xref target="RFC4566"/>.</t>

     <t>In the <xref target="gateway-cons">gateway configuration section</xref> replacement of the first sentence "This section describes the network configuration where one endpoint runs MSRP over a WebRTC SCTP/DTLS connection, the other MSRP endpoint runs MSRP over one or more  TLS/TCP connections, and the two endpoints interwork via an MSRP gateway" with "This section describes the network configuration where one MSRP endpoint uses data channels as MSRP transport, the other MSRP endpoint uses TLS/TCP connections as MSRP transport, and the two MSRP endpoints interwork via an MSRP gateway".</t>

    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against 'draft-ejzak-mmusic-msrp-usage-data-channel-01'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t>Removed empty spaces after ";" in the examples' "a=dcmap" attribute lines.</t>

     <t>In all examples, the "m=" line proto value "DTLS/SCTP" was replaced with "UDP/DTLS/SCTP" and the "a=fmtp" attribute lines were replaced with "a=max-message-size" attribute lines, as per draft-ietf-mmusic-sctp-sdp-12.</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Changes against '-00'">
   <t>
    <list style="symbols">
     <t> Transport parameter change for MSRP to allow MSRP RFC transports.</t>

     <t> Clarification on SDP offer/answer and removing duplicated procedures and refer them to draft-ejzak-mmusic-data-channel-sdpneg-02.</t>

    </list>
   </t>

  </section>

 </section>

</middle>

<!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

<back>
 <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

 <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
  1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
  2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
  (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

  Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
  If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
  directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
  with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
  filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->


 <references title="Normative References">

   &RFC2119;
   &DATAPROTO;
   &DATAREQ;
   &DCSDPNEG;
   &SDPSCTP;
   &RFC4566;
   &RFC4975;
   &RFC5547;
   &RFC6135;
   &RFC6714;
   &RFC7977;

 </references>

</back>

</rfc>
